A Guide to the Historical Postcards, 1900-1980
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Historical Postcards 1900-1980
Thomas Balch Library
VC 0004
.15 cu. ft.
The primary subject matter of the postcards is scenes from around Loudoun County, although there are images from surrounding Virginia counties and several cards related to Harpers Ferry, West Virginia. Buildings, images of nature, and well-known streets figure prominently. Leesburg is the location most covered, including many images of Market Street, King Street, and the Loudoun County Courthouse.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Ethel Littlejohn Adams, Leesburg, VA; Emory Plaster, Leesburg, VA; unknown.
Alternative Form Available
Digital reproductions
Accruals
1988.0001, 1991.0002, 1995.0039X.
Historical Information
Postcards developed out of the complex tradition of nineteenth-century printed calling cards, beginning with the advent of the Cartes-de-Visite in France. In the 1850s, Parisian photographer Andre Adolphe Eugene Disderi invented a photographic process involving egg white, albumen, and silver nitrate to create inexpensive portraits on paper cards. These photographic Cartes-de-Visites were 2 1/2 by 4 inches and became a popular, collectable form of "visiting cards" world-wide. Photographers would reprint portraits of famous individuals they had taken at their studios or during travel and sell them as collectable cards. Public figures such as European royalty, military generals, doctors, and businessmen would pose for Cartes-de-Visite portraits that were used as trading cards, business cards, and advertisements. During the American Civil War such cards were taxed, with revenue stamps affixed to the back.
Postcards as we know them now first began in 1861 as cards mailed by private post, invented by American John P. Charlton of Philadelphia with the patent later transferred to Philadelphian H. L. Lipman. Prussian postman Heinrich von Stephan advocated government-issued postcards in 1865. In 1869 the first government-created postal cards were printed in Hungary and the first cards for private post were printed in Austria. In the 1870s picture postcards grew in popularity throughout the United States, Britain, Europe, and Japan. China created regulations for postcards in 1896 and began printing them in 1898.
In 1873 the United States Government began to issue the only postal cards legal in the U.S., of plain card stock with no artistic design on the front. On 19 May 1898, Congress passed the Private Mailing Act, which allowed the mailing of privately printed post cards marked "Private Mailing Card." Only this designation, the address, and the stamp were permitted on the back; any message had to be written over the artwork which publishers printed on the front of the card. The Act also reduced the postage rate for the cards from the two cent letter rate to one cent. Beginning on 24 December 1901, relaxed regulations authorized private printers in the United States to drop "Private Mailing Card" in favor of "Post Card" or "Postcard."
During the "Undivided Back" period printers began to leave white space on the front of the card where the sender could write a message without spoiling the artwork (see VC 0004_3000). Cards were first permitted to have a "Divided Back," with text written on the left half of a dividing line and the address on the right half, beginning in England in 1902. France switched to a divided back in 1904, Germany in 1905, and the United States on 1 March 1907 (VC 0004_3025).
Around 1900 the first postcards made of "Real Photos" rather than artwork began to circulate, aided in by advances in amateur photography equipment by companies such as Kodak. Kodak also introduced postcard paper for photographic development and photography studios began to offer portraits printed as postcards (see VC 0004_2504). Many local town, countryside, and architectural images were captured during this period by local photographers, then printed and sold as postcards (see VC 0004_1708).
The loosening of government regulation, lowered costs, and advances in amateur photography all contributed to a postcard craze that lasted from 1900 to the First World War. Postcards were the preferred means to send a quick note, whether across town or across a continent. U.S. postal records for fiscal year 1907-1908 indicate over 677 million postcards mailed.
German printers' fine artwork and superior processes allowed Germany to dominate the market until the outbreak of war in 1914 (see VC 0004_3017). European printers opened offices in the United States and postcard artists moved to Germany. When war halted the flow of high-quality German cards, English and American producers attempted to fill market demand. Their processes, however, resulted in cards of inferior quality. From the War to 1930 cards were printed with a white border around the edge to bring down high printing costs by saving ink (see VC 0004_3038). Lower quality contributed to the demise of postcard mania.
Although new linen paper processes in the 1930s resulted in better quality, more brightly colored card art (see VC 0004_3037), the postcard industry continued to decline. After 1939, new Photochromes, color photo postcards, began to replace both linen and black and white photo postcards (see VC 0004_0200). By the end of World War II these "Chromes" had completely replaced other card forms. The widely available telephone replaced the postcard for sending short messages and postcards became largely confined to the realm of souvenirs (see VC 0004_0600). Though postcards continue to be produced, they would never regain the enormous popularity of the early twentieth century.
Scope and Content
The majority of the approximately 170 postcards in the collection fall between 1901 and World War I and are Undivided Back or early Divided Back cards. The bulk of the remaining postcards fall between World War I and the end of World War II, including several examples of linen paper cards. The remaining postcards are Photochrome cards from the 1970s or 80s.
The primary subject matter of the postcards is scenes from around Loudoun County, although there are images from surrounding Virginia counties and several cards related to Harpers Ferry, West Virginia. Buildings, images of nature, and well-known streets figure prominently. Leesburg is the location most covered, including many images of Market Street, King Street, and the Loudoun County Courthouse.
Arrangement
Geographic
0100 Ashburn
0200 Ashby's Gap
0300 Berryville
0400 Bluemont
0500 Charles Town, WV
0600 Dulles
0700 Elvan
0800 Georgetown
0900 Hamilton
1000 Harpers Ferry, WV
1100 Hillsboro
1200 Lexington
1300 Lincoln
1400 Luray
1500 Natural Bridge
1600 Paeonian Springs
1700 Purcellville
1800 Red Hill
1900 Round Hill
2000 Ryan
2100 Shenandoah Valley & National Park
2200 Staunton
2300 Waterford
2400 Historic memorabilia
2500 Portraits
2600 Lucketts
2700 Middleburg
3000 Leesburg
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
American Postcard Art.Com Inc.: About Postcards by Phil Neigh.
Emotions Greeting Cards/VH Productions: The History of Postcards by Vivian Krug, 2003. http://www.emotionscards.com/museum/historyofpostcards.htm (accessed 1 Aug 2007)
Hemsath, DiAnna. Postcards: Penn College Girls. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Archives, 2006. http://www.archives.upenn.edu/memorabilia/postcards/collegegirls.html (accessed 1 August 2007)
Lisa's Postcard Page: A Brief History of Postcard Types by Stefano Neis. http://www.geocities.com/Heartland/Meadows/2487/pchistory.htm (accessed 1 August 2007)
Postcards as Face to Face: A Brief History of the Postcard by Chien-chun Tsao, 1998. http://www.post-card.net/history.html (accessed 1 August 2007)
Other Finding Aid
None
Contents List
- (Box Historical Postcards)
  - School House, Ashburn, VA, 1900 D
  - View from Ashby's Gap, 1980 C
  - Abbey Guesthouse, 1980
  - Air View Holy Cross Abbey, 1980
  - U.S. Weather Bureau, Bluemont, VA [text on front], n.d.
  - John Brown Wagon, 1950 C
  - Washington's Dulles International Airport is an international gateway to this country through Washington, our nation's capital. It is a jet airport of both beauty and efficiency, offering the most modern facilities to all its visitors. 1970 C
  - Mt. Olivet M.E. Church, Elvan, VA [text on front], 1907
  - Gen. George Washington's Headquarters, M St between 30th & 31st St NW, DC, 1910 C
  - John Brown's Fort, Harper's Ferry, W. VA, 1910 C
  - John Brown's Monument and War Tablets from B. & O. Station, 1922
  - Looking Towards the Junction of the Potomac and Shenandoah Rivers, 1920 D
  - Harper's Ferry, W. VA, from Loudoun Heights on Main Line--Baltimore & Ohio Railroad, 1920 D
  - Jefferson Rock, Harper's Ferry W. VA. [text on back], 1900
  - The Harper House, Built 1780, by Robert Harper, the Founder of Harpers Ferry, 1900
  - View of the Gap from Hill Top House, 1900
  - Looking Down the Gap from Marist Hill, 1900
  - Gen. Robert E. Lee on "Traveler." Gen. E. Lee on Traveler was taken by Miley of Lexington, Va. At Washington & Lee College in 1869. Lee was born Jan. 19, 1807 and died Oct. 12, 1870, age 63 years, 8 months, 23 days. 1920 C
  - High School Building, Lincoln, VA, 1910 C
  - Lincoln High School, 1930 C
  - The former Lyceum Hall, lincoln, Loudoun County, Virginia. Built in 1874, this building now houses A.M. Janney & Son - the finest store in town. 1980 C
  - The Road to Stony Man Mountain Shenandoah National Park. THE MIMSLYN, Hotel of Distinction near Shenandoah National Park and Beautiful Caverns Luray, Virginia, 1915 C
  - Natural Bridge Hotel, Natural Bridge, VA, 1920 C
  - Fan Tail Falls, Southwest Virginia [Poem: "In Old Virginia"], 1920 C
  - Paeonian Springs, Virginia. The Paeonian Springs Academy held classes from 1903 until 1930. Begun by John Simpson as a private school, it joined the public school system in 1910. The building, located along Rte. 9, is now a private residence. 1930 C
  - Paeonian Springs, Virginia. In the early 1900s, the Paeonian Springs Depot bustled with activity as the Washington and Old Dominion Railroad provided train service to this quaint resort village. 1900 C
  - Purcellville, VA [copy of postcard of downtown Purcellville, c. 1909], 1900 C
  - [Buggies, woman, and power lines in front of J T Cornwell Groceries & Meats & Purcellville Pharmacy], 1900 C
  - Main Street. Residential Section, Purcellville, VA [copy of postcard], 1900 C
  - The Auditorium, Purcellville, VA, 1907
  - Bank Block - Purcellville VA, 1911
  - Bushmeeting, Purcellville, VA, 1900 C
  - Public Library Purcellville VA, 1930 C
  - School Fair Parade, Purcellville, VA, 1915 C
  - School Fair Parade, Purcellville, VA, 1915
  - Home of Patrick Henry, 1920 C
  - Loudoun Valley, Round Hill, VA, 1910 C
  - Lovers' Retreat At Bear's Den, Near Round Hill, VA, 1920 C
  - The Village Brook Round Hill, VA, 1910 C
  - Will Be Looking For You At Round Hill Station. 1910 C
  - Greetings from RYAN, VA [man and wagon in hay field], 1920
  - Greetings from RYAN, VA [cows in field], 1920
  - Apple Blossom Time in the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia, 1920 C
  - Panoramic View, from Buck Hollow Overlook. Shenandoah National Park, Virginia, 1970 C
  - Birthplace of Woodrow Wilson, Staunton, VA. Woodrow Wilson, son of Rev. Joseph R. Wilson, Staunton Presbyterian minister, was born in Staunton Dec. 8, 1856, at the Presbyterian mass. World War President 1912 to 1920. 1920 C
  - Barracks, Augusta Military Academy, Fort Defiance, Near Staunton, VA, 1920 C
  - Fairfax Meeting House Farm Waterford, Virginia, 1960 C
  - Friends Meeting House, Waterford, VA. Built 1775. 1906 C
  - Lower Main Street, Waterford, VA, 1907
  - The Old Mill-- Waterford, VA near Leesburg, Virginia, 1950 C
  - An Old Street In Waterford, VA, 1911
  - Main Street, Waterford, VA, 1950 C
  - [Post Office, Waterford, VA], 1988
  - [Country Store, Waterford, VA], 1974 C
  - Washington, the Father of his Country [Washington with leaves & cherries], 1910 C
  - Washington, the Father of his Country [Washington portrait with flag], 1910 C
  - Washington, the Father of his Country [Washington portrait], 1910 C
  - Washington Febr. 22d 1732 Dec. 14th 1799 [Washington portrait], 1910 C
  - Flags of the Confederacy "And twill live in song and story, Though its folds are in the dust" [information about flags on lower face], 1930 C
  - Lucy Wering McCabe. Age 5 years. 1900 C
  - [Catherine Newman], 1910 C
  - [Mary Kate Beamer], 1910 C
  - [Reardon Children Portrait], 1900 C
  - [Unknown man portrait], 1900 C
  - [Unknown man and woman portrait], 1917 C
  - A Few of the "Old Timers" Still Living at Leesburg, VA, 1903
  - Loudoun Camp Meeting-- At Home, 1907
  - "Carlheim" Leesburg, VA, 1900
  - "Carlheim," Residence of Mrs. R.A. Paxton, Leesburg, VA, 1910
  - County Clerk's Office Building, Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - Loudoun County Clerk's Office, Leesburg, VA, 1940 C
  - Old Court House where President James Monroe presided as Justice, Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Old Court House where President James Monroe presided as Justice, Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Court House of Loudoun County, 1900 C
  - Court House, Leesburg, VA, 1906
  - The Children who unveiled the Confederate Monument at Leesburg, VA, May 28, 1908. 1908
  - Confederate Monument, Leesburg, VA, 1908
  - Confederate Monument, Leesburg, VA, 1908
  - Confederate Monument, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Court House and Confederate Monument. Leesburg, VA, 1909 C
  - Confederate Monument--Erected to the Confederate dead of Loudoun Co. Unveiled May 28th, 1908, 1909 C
  - Court House and Clerk's Office of Loudoun County, Leesburg, VA, 1914
  - Court House and Market St., Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Loudoun County Court House and Confederate Monument Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Loudoun County Court House Leesburg, Virginia, 1930 C
  - "Belmont." Built in 1800 by Ludwell Lee Residence of Hon. Patrick J. Hurley, Former Secretary of War Near Leesburg, Virginia, 1938
  - "Belmont," near Leesburg, VA. Residence of the Hon. Patrick J. Hurley, Former Secretary of War. This Mansion Was Built in 1800 by Ludwell Lee, Son of Richard Henry Lee, Signer of the Declaration of Independence. 1938
  - "Belmont," near Leesburg, VA. Residence of the Hon. Patrick J Hurley, Former Secretary of War. This Mansion was Built in 1800 by Ludwell Lee, Son of Richard Henry Lee, Signer of the Declaration of Independence. 1955
  - "Belmont," near Leesburg, VA. Residence of George C. Clarke, Hotel Owner and Lawyer, Washington, D.C. This Mansion was built in 1800 by Ludwell Lee, Son of Richard Henry Lee, Signer of the Declaration of Independence. 1950 C
  - Dodona Manor - Home of General & Mrs. George C. Marshall - Leesburg, Virginia, n.d.
  - [Text on front: "Residence of G W Hevener Leesburg, VA"], 1908
  - John Champ's House, During the Revolution, 1776. Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Leesburg High School, 1905
  - High School Building, Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Leesburg High School Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - Leesburg High School Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - High School Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Leesburg High School, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Leesburg Inn, 1905 C
  - The Inn Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Leesburg Inn and Confederate Monument, 1930 C
  - Leesburg Inn Leesburg, Virginia. Located on Routes 7 and 15. 37 Scenic Miles from Washington, D. C. Very Reasonable Rates Fine Southern-cooked Food S. W. Keesee, Owner. 1930 C
  - The Inn Leesburg, Virginia Located on Routes 7 and 15. 37 Scenic Miles from Washington, D.C. Very Reasonable Rates Fine Southern-cooked Food S. W. Keesee, Owner. 1940 C
  - Loudoun Hospital and Nurses Home, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Loudoun County Hospital Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - Morven Park, Home of ex-Governor Westmoreland Davis, Leesburg, VA, n.d.
  - Morven Park Estates, Home of Ex-Governor Westmoreland Davis Leesburg, VA, n.d.
  - Old Log House, Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Old Methodist Church, Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Old Methodist Church, Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Old Stone Church Built In 1785. The First Conference of the Methodist Church in Virginia was held in this old building at Leesburg, VA. 1900 C
  - Old Stone Church, The first Conference of the Methodist Church in America was held in this old building in Leesburg, VA. Built in 1785. 1900 C
  - The Old Stone Church Where The First Methodist Conference Held In America Assembled. 1905 C
  - M.E. Church South, 1905 C
  - U.S. Post Office, Leesburg, VA, 1940 C
  - Post Office Leesburg, VA, 1952
  - R. R. Depot, Leesburg, VA, 1912
  - Entrance from Railroad Station, Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - Presbyterian Church. Built in 1804 Leesburg, VA. 1930 C
  - St. James Episcopal Church Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - Leesburg, VA. St. James Episcopal Church, 1905 C
  - St. James' Church Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - Interior View of Old St. James Church As It Appeared, Christmas 1895. 1895
  - "Selma" Home of Co. E. B. White Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Springwood Home of Mr. S. S. Lutz. Waverly Home of Mr. Robt. T. Hempstone, 1900 C
  - Thomas Balch Library Leesburg, Virginia, 1930 C
  - The Wildman Co., Dry Goods Store, Leesburg, VA. Established 1847. 1906
  - Central View in Leesburg, 1966
  - King Street, Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - King Street, Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - Winter Scene, King St. Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - King Street. Leesburg, VA, 1907 C
  - King Street looking South from Market Street, Leesburg, VA, 1925 C
  - King Street, Leesburg, VA, 1925 C
  - King Street Leesburg, VA, 1925 C
  - North King Street, Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - King Street, North from Market Street Leesburg, VA, 1930 C
  - South King Street. Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Looking North on South King Street, Leesburg, VA, 1900 C
  - Thompson-Plaster X Ray Co., King and Loudoun Streets Leesburg, VA, 1926 C
  - Thompson-Plaster X Ray Co., King and Loudoun Streets Leesburg, VA], 1926
  - Lafayette's Headquarters, Leesburg, VA, 1905 C
  - Washington's Headquarters, Loudoun Street Leesburg, VA, 1929
  - Washington's Headquarters, Leesburg 1930 C
  - The Worsley and Alexander Houses on Loudoun Street. Leesburg, VA. Where Washington was entertained, also Lafayette on his return visit August 9th, 1825. 1930 C
  - Loudoun Street, showing Stone House at left in which Washington was entertained during Revolution, also where Lafayette was welcomed August 9, 1825, Leesburg, VA, 1933
  - The Home where Gen. Lafayette was entertained during his visit to Leesburg, VA, 1940 C
  - Market Street, Leesburg, VA, 1905 C
  - Parting of the Ways 1905 C
  - East Market and Fayette Streets, Leesburg, VA, 1910
  - Parting of the Ways, East Market and Fayette Streets. Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Parting of the Ways. Western approaches to Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - House in which Wm Wirt once lived on Wirt St., Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - West view, from water tower, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Greetings from Leesburg, VA [gravel road through trees with car], 1920 C
  - Greetings from Leesburg, VA [cows in field], 1920 C
  - Ball's Bluff Battlefield Leesburg, VA, 1905 C
  - "Ball's Bluff" over which U.S. Troops fled from the battle of the same name Oct. 21st 1862. 1910
  - National Cemetery and part of Ball's Battlefield, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - National Cemetery on Battlefield, Ball's Bluff, near Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Balls Bluff Cemetery is located on Rt. 15 two miles north of Leesburg, Virginia. It is the site of the only major battle of the Civil War in Loudoun County and one of the smallest National cemeteries. 1980 C
  - Big Spring, Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - Big Spring near Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Big Spring near Leesburg, VA, 1907
  - Big Spring near Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - Blue Ridge Mountains near Leesburg, VA, 1950 C
  - Goose Creek Bridge on Washington Turnpike Leesburg, VA, 1950 C
  - Goose Creek Bridge on Washington Turnpike Leesburg, VA, 1950 C
  - Goose Creek Dam. Leesburg, VA, 1926
  - Looking across the Potomac at White's Ferry, Leesburg, VA, 1920 C
  - Potomac River at White's Ferry Leesburg, VA, 1950 C
  - Potomac River at White's Ferry Leesburg, VA, 1950 C
  - Tuscarora bridge, Leesburg, VA, 1910 C
  - R.V. Brundage - Rental - Contract - 3/4 yd. Shovel - Crane - Clam - Backhoe Phone 99 Leesburg, VA, 1960 C
  - Loudoun Museum and Log Cabin, n.d.
  - Oatlands, n.d.
  - White's Ferry, n.d.
  - Town Hall and Parking Structure, Leesburg, VA, n.d.
  - Col. John Singleton Mosby, n.d.
  - Thomas Balch Library, shortly after completion, c. 1922
  - Thomas Balch Library, photo courtesy of Jim Hanna Photography, n.d.
  - Winter comes to the Xerox International Center for Training and Management Development, 35 miles northwest of Washington D.C., near Leesburg, Virginia. n.d.
  - Confederate Monument, n.d.
  - King of the Western Punchers, n.d.
  - Thompson-Plaster X Ray Co., King and Loudoun Streets, Leesburg, VA, n.d.
  - "Belmont," near Leesburg, VA, n.d.
  - Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA, n.d.